Indiana University President's Office Correspondence, 1913-1937 C286
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University President's Office correspondence
1913-1937
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. President
C286
294.4 cubic feet 295 boxes
William Lowe Bryan served as president of Indiana University 1902-1937. This collection consists almost entirely of incoming correspondence from the years 1913-1937. The files are arranged alphabetically, most often by the correspondent's surname, but also by subject or by name of the institution or department. The majority of the correspondence is addressed to Bryan but much of it is also addressed to other high ranking IU administrators such as Registrar John W. Cravens or University Secretary Ulysses Howe Smith.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
BRYAN, William Lowe (11 Nov. 1860-21 Nov. 1955), philosopher, psychologist, and educator, was born William Julian Bryan on a farm near Bloomington, Indiana, the son of John Bryan, a Presbyterian minister, and Eliza Jane Philips. In 1876 he entered the preparatory department of Indiana University in Bloomington, which served as the local high school, and the next year he matriculated as a university student. As an undergraduate he developed his skills in public speaking and helped to revive the Indiana Student newspaper in 1882. He became a member of the Specialists' Club organized by David Starr Jordan, professor of natural sciences, to encourage promising students to pursue research careers. Bryan graduated in 1884 with a bachelor's degree in ancient classics.
After graduation Bryan was hired as an English instructor in the preparatory department. Within a few months he received an unexpected opportunity to join the regular faculty when the president of the university, Baptist minister Lemuel Moss, and Katherine Graydon, the professor of Greek, were caught up in a romantic scandal and left the university. Bryan was hired as Graydon's replacement, and in early 1885 Jordan was appointed president. Jordan, a noted ichthyologist, placed science at the center of his ideas on educational reform and stressed that the highest function of the real university is that of instruction by investigation. Working with limited financial support from the state he relied heavily on local talent to fill the ranks of the faculty.
Although Bryan earned a master's degree in philosophy at Indiana in 1886 with a thesis on ancient Greek logic, his interests shifted toward the new psychology that promised to revolutionize the study of human nature through laboratory experimentation and other empirical techniques. He went to Germany, the center of scientific psychology, in 1886-1887 to study at the University of Berlin; after returning he was promoted to full professor and granted $100 to purchase a Hipp chronoscope for experimental studies of human reaction times. In January 1888 Bryan opened the Indiana University Psychological laboratory, the second such facility established in the United States.
Bryan married Charlotte Augusta Lowe in 1889 and in her honor replaced his given middle name with her last name. His wife was a graduate of Indiana University, having earned a bachelor's degree (1888) and a master's degree (1889) in Greek. They collaborated on two books, Plato the Teacher: Selections from Plato (1897) and Studies in Plato's Republic for Teachers (1898). They had no children.
Bryan carried a heavy teaching load, and at first the psychological laboratory was used mainly for classroom demonstrations rather than original research. In 1891 he went to Clark University to pursue a doctorate under G. Stanley Hall, a prominent advocate of the new psychology. Bryan received his Ph.D. in psychology in 1892 for a dissertation on the development of voluntary motor abilities in children. He was also recruited by Hall to help organize the American Psychological Association, founded in July 1892, and became one of its twenty-six charter members.
After returning to Indiana University, Bryan expanded the psychological laboratory and was appointed vice president of the institution. He resisted repeated offers by Jordan, who had become president of Stanford University in 1891, to join the faculty of the California school. Bryan also became involved in the child-study movement, an effort to develop a scientific foundation for pedagogical techniques. He served as an officer in several national organizations, including the secretary of the National Association for the Study of Children (1893) and the president of the Child-Study Section of the National Educational Association (1894).
In the 1890s Bryan conducted pioneering psychological experiments. He investigated the process of learning to send and receive messages in Morse code on the telegraph. The research, published in the Psychological Review (1897, 1899), was among the first such studies to graphically represent its data in the form of learning curves and became a classic in the study of human learning. Because of Bryan's efforts, during this period Indiana University became an undergraduate training ground for notable future psychologists, including Edwin D. Starbuck, Ernest H. Lindley, and Lewis M. Terman.
In 1902 Bryan was appointed the tenth president of Indiana University. The next year he was elected president of the American Psychological Association and delivered his presidential address on the problem of Theory and Practice (repr., Psychological Review 11 [1904]: 71-82). His remark that the scholar may at great price become a statesman suggested his ambivalence about leaving the laboratory for administration.
Pious and scholarly, Bryan presided over the transformation of Indiana University from a small, traditional liberal arts college into a modern research university. He led the institution for thirty-five years and oversaw an era of enormous growth in student enrollments, physical facilities, and curricular offerings. He considered administration an exercise in practical psychology and viewed the university as a key institution for the transmission of cultural values as well as specialized knowledge. His most notable accomplishment was the expansion of graduate and professional training. During his administration, schools of medicine, education, nursing, business, music, and dentistry were established, along with many graduate programs and several satellite campuses around the state. By the time Bryan retired at the age of seventy-six, Indiana University had significantly broadened access to its programs and had dramatically increased the quality of graduate and professional education.
Bryan was known as a pithy orator, and his speeches were highly moralistic. His strong belief in the scientific study of human nature was tempered by an equally powerful conviction that it was not sufficient to provide moral and spiritual guidance. Hence he maintained an interest in ethics and metaphysics throughout his life. In 1940 Bryan published Wars of Families of Minds, a book that reflected on the consequences of different ways of knowing the world. A colleague once called him a philosopher tamed by science--a characterization that could have easily been applied to Bryan's intellectual hero, William James.
After retirement Bryan continued to live on campus in the president's house, and he remained a familiar sight walking along its wooded paths. He died in Bloomington. The institution he developed commemorated his work with many memorials, including the William Lowe Bryan Hall, the main administration building at Indiana University, and his hometown also named in his honor Bryan Park, a large municipal park.
* Bryan's papers are in the Indiana University Archives. On his university administration, see Thomas D. Clark, Indiana University: Midwestern Pioneer, vol. 2 (1973), and Burton Dorr Myers, History of Indiana University, 1902-1937, the Bryan Administration (1952). Bryan's career as a psychologist is described in Eliot Hearst and James H. Capshew, eds., Psychology at Indiana University: A Centennial Review and Compendium (1988), which also contains a comprehensive bibliography of his writings. Additional biographical material can be found in Manfred Wolfe Deputy, The Philosophical Ideas and Related Achievements of William Lowe Bryan (Ph.D. diss., Indiana Univ., 1947). Major obituaries are in the American Journal of Psychology 69 (1956): 325-27; Science 123 (1956): 214; and the New York Times, 22 Nov. 1955.
Written by James H. Capshew
Arrangement
This collection maintains the original order ascribed by the Office of the President. In instances where items cannot be directly associated with a topical subject, they are filed alphabetically under the proper name of the document's creator. The majority of the documents, however, are filed alphabetically according to topic.
Scope and Content Note
The contents of this collection represent records created and collected during the latter half of President William Lowe Bryan's tenure, 1913-1937. (Records dating from 1902-1913 can be found in Collection C270.) Arranged alphabetically by subject or correspondent's surname, the collection consists of of correspondence, publications, and reports relating to university operations and major events within the university system and the local and academic communities.
Highlights of the collection include: materials relating to the Olmsted Brothers; correspondence with prominent IU professors and administrators, such as W.A. Alexander, George A. Ball, Ward G. Biddle, R.E. Cavanaugh, Frank R. Elliott, James W. Fesler, Alfred Kinsey, Robert W. Long, Burton D. Myers, Mrs. Alice Nelson, W.A. Rawles, Henry Lester Smith, Ulysses H. Smith, Stith Thompson, Herman B Wells, Ora Wildermuth, and James Woodburn; various other universities such as University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and Purdue University; and other topics and institutions including Prohibition, the Rhodes Trust, the State Department of Public Instruction, the United States Veterans and War Departments, and the Young Men's Christian Association (Y.M.C.A.).
The records in this collection represent the bulk of the records from William Lowe Bryan's tenure as president of IU. However, additions may be made to these records periodically as they are found in other accessions. Please ask Archives staff for more details.
Related Material
Collection C270, Indiana University President's Office correspondence, 1902-1913. Collection C71, President William Lowe Bryan speeches, 1903-1937. Collection C69, William Lowe Bryan papers, 1830-1960.
Acquisition Information
0134 + others
College presidents --Indiana --Archives.; College presidents --Indiana --Correspondence.; Universities and colleges --Indiana --Administration; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955 -- Correspondence; Bryan, William Lowe, 1860-1955 -- Archives; Indiana University -- Administration; Indiana University. President -- Archives; Indiana University. President -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. President -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
- Subject files, 1913-1937 (Box 1)
  - A, 1915-1937 (Box 1)
  - A List, 1934-1937 (Box 1)
  - A Students, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Aaron, Alice, 1931-1932 (Box 1)
  - Aaronsohn, Michael, 1923-1927 (Box 1)
  - Aatell & Jones Inc, 1927-1934 (Box 1)
  - Ab (Box 1)
    - 1914-1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abbett, M.J., 1918-1932 (Box 1)
  - Abbett, M.J., 1933-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abbet, Roscoe O., 1916-1924 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Charles W., 1916-1925 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Charlotte, 1914-1925 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Clarence C., 1915-1918 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Cornelius, 1931-1936 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Elizabeth, 1928-1933 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, John E., 1936 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Livonia W., 1930-1932 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Louise A., 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Lyman E., 1920-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Mrs. Mary, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Mayme, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Talbert W., 1914-1923 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, U.S., 1924-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abbott, Wilbur C., 1920-1935 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Anna G., 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Cecil R., 1928-1930 (Box 1)
  - Abel, James W., 1927-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Josephine, 1916-1933 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Rose, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Ruth, 1918-1930 (Box 1)
  - Abel, William L., 1924-1930 (Box 1)
  - Abel, Zaula Z., 1914-1929 (Box 1)
  - Abell Elevator Company, 1915-1931 (Box 1)
  - Abell, Alice, 1925-1934 (Box 1)
  - Abell, E.L., 1922-1931 (Box 1)
  - Abell, J.A., 1914-1935 (Box 1)
  - Abell, Julian D., 1923-1928 (Box 1)
  - Abell, Lucille, 1927-1935 (Box 1)
  - Abell, Thelma L., 1925-1937 (Box 1)
  - Aber, Floyd J., 1919 (Box 1)
  - Abercrombie Fitch Company, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Abercrombie, John S., 1934-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abercrombie, John W., 1915-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abercrombie, Laurett, 1928-1931 (Box 1)
  - Abercrombie, Mary Ann, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Abernathy, Bruce, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Abernathy, Charles C., 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Abernathy, Mildred, 1916-1921 (Box 1)
  - Abernathy, Thomas, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Press, 1922-1929 (Box 1)
  - Abner, Bertha Beery, 1926-1931 (Box 1)
  - Abner, John Riley, 1927-1930 (Box 1)
  - Abraham, Alice T., 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Abraham Lincoln University, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Abrahamson, Ivar M., 1924-1927 (Box 1)
  - Abrams, Charles G., 1928-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abrams, M.D., 1923-1926 (Box 1)
  - Abrell, Clee Otis, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
  - Abrell, Elsworth, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Abrell, Mary K., 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - Abrell, Faye Calvert, 1926-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abrell, Gail, 1925-1934 (Box 1)
  - Abridged Compendium of American Genealogy, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Absence, 1915-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abshier, Ione, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
  - Abston, Bernice, 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Ac (Box 1)
    - 1914-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1927 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1937 (Box 1)
  - Acacia Fraternity, 1919-1936 (Box 1)
  - Academic Costume, 1928-1937 (Box 1)
  - Academic Freedom, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Academy of the Immaculate Conception, 1924-1933 (Box 1)
  - Academy of Natural Sciences, 1915-1931 (Box 1)
  - Academy of Political Science, 1926-1937 (Box 1)
  - Academy of Science, 1924-1934 (Box 1)
  - Accident, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
  - Accountants, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Accounting, 1924-1937 (Box 1)
  - Accredited/Accrediting, 1926-1936 (Box 1)
  - Acher, Rudolph A., 1918-1921 (Box 1)
  - Acher, Virginia, 1916-1927 (Box 1)
  - Achong, Tipo P., 1916 (Box 1)
  - Achor, Harold E., 1928 (Box 1)
  - Achttien, Anna E., 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Ackeis, Margaret, 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - Acker, Jessica, 1921-1922 (Box 1)
  - Acker, Julius W., 1928-1932 (Box 1)
  - Acker, Margaret, 1914-1915 (Box 1)
  - Acker, Phil, 1927-1936 (Box 1)
  - Ackert, Kathryn, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Emory, 1915-1916 (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Joyce, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Mary Elizabeth, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Merle, 1928-1932 (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, W.A., 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Acheson Graphite Company, 1914-1920 (Box 1)
  - ACME Bonding & Fidelity Company, 1931 (Box 1)
  - ACME Card System Co., 1917-1923 (Box 1)
  - ACME Folding Boat Company, 1917 (Box 1)
  - ACME Mill Ends Co., 1917-1920 (Box 1)
  - ACME Teacher's Agency, 1923-1927 (Box 1)
  - ACME Towel-Linen Supply Co., 1917 (Box 1)
  - Acord, Mabel, 1930-1936 (Box 1)
  - Acoustics, 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Acre, Harian G., 1914-1919 (Box 1)
  - Acre, R.R., 1915-1923 (Box 1)
  - Action Film Company, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Activities Fees, 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Activities- Miscellaneous, 1927-1935 (Box 1)
  - Activities Office, 1935-1937 (Box 1)
  - Activity Books, 1926-1935 (Box 1)
  - Acton, Indiana, 1926-1937 (Box 1)
  - Acts, 1915-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adahan-Adams., 1913-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adair, J.A.M., 1914-1916 (Box 1)
  - Adair, Jewell, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Adair, Joseph, 1923-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adair, Mabel, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Alberta, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Alice, 1917-1928 (Box 1)
  - Adams, A.M., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Amelia, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Adams and Grace Company, 1921-1924 (Box 1)
  - Adams and Peck, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Arthur, 1932-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams-Bagnall Electric Co., 1916 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Benjamin F., 1913-1918 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Bertha, 1915-1922 (Box 1)
  - Adams, C.F., 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Claude, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Adams Clay Products Co., 1925-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams County Scholarships, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Dale, 1927-1932 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Darrel L., 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - Adams, David Hollis, 1926-1932 (Box 1)
  - Adams, D.F., 1923-1924 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Don (D.G.), 1917-1929 (Box 1)
  - Adams, D.S., 1924-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Edna, 1919-1922 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Eleanor, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Elizabeth, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Elmer, 1926-1931 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Eloise, 1927-1932 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Elsie, 1920-1934 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Esther, 1920-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Estryl, 1926-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams, E. Virginia, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams Express Company, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Frances, 1920-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Frank H., 1932-1934 (Box 1)
  - Adams, George, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Gilbert P., 1919-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Grace G., 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Guy S., 1916-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Harold W., 1914-1926 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Helen, 1916-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Henry, 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Herschel Enoch, 1927-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Hollis, 1926-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Horton K., 1926-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Howard Webster, 1914-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Jacob A., 1918-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, James E., 1924-1933 (Box 1)
  - Adams, James L., 1926-1928 (Box 1)
  - Adams, James S., 1922-1935 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Jane, 1924-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Jesse E., 1918-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Jim, 1923-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, John E., 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Adams, John L., 1914-1936 (Box 1)
  - Adams, John Philip, 1924-1931 (Box 1)
  - Adams, John W., 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Josephine, 1913-1923 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Lawrence, 1923-1927 (Box 1)
  - Adams, L.M. Campbell, 1913-1926 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Louise, 1928-1932 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Louis Phillip, 1914-1923 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Margaret, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Martin A., 1923-1928 (Box 1)
  - Adams, Mary, 1918-1933 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary Alice, 1921-1924 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary B., 1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary C., 1923-1928 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary E., 1925-1936 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary Emma, 1927-1934 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mary M., 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Maude, 1914-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Maurice D., 1926-1933 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Max, 1921-1929 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Maxine, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Mildred, 1926-1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Muriel, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Myra, 1916-1921 (Box 2)
  - Adams, N.E., 1924-1926 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Nellie, 1924-1936 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Norval E., 1929-1930 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Otie, 1915-1916 (Box 2)
  - Adams, R.A., 1925-1931 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Ralph, 1919-1931 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Raymond, 1926-1934 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Reuben, 1918-1925 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Robert, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Rowland C., 1930-1935 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Ruth, 1923-1927 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Sarah, 1927-1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Shelby C., 1916-1936 (Box 2)
  - Adams-Smith and Thurston Teaching Agency, 1924-1926 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Una D., 1915-1927 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Vesta D., 1925-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Virginia, 1930-1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Waldo, 1921-1924 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Wayman, 1913-1936 (Box 2)
  - Adams, W.E., 1922-1924 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Will H., 1931-1935 (Box 2)
  - Adams, William H., 1916-1932 (Box 2)
  - Adams, W.L., 1925-1935 (Box 2)
  - Adams, Zella, 1916-1925 (Box 2)
  - Adamson-Advocate, 1913-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Doris W., 1930-1935 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, D.W., 1919-1929 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, James H., 1926-1931 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Margaret, 1922-1926 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Mary, 1930-1935 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Ralph E., 1924-1927 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Robert, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - Adamson, Wendell, 1925-1937 (Box 2)
  - Addams, Jane, 1915-1920 (Box 2)
  - Addington, A. Everette, 1915-1923 (Box 2)
  - Addington, Archie, 1916-1937 (Box 2)
  - Addington, E. (A.), 1925-1928 (Box 2)
  - Addington, Ray R., 1927-1935 (Box 2)
  - Addington, Sarah, 1924-1926 (Box 2)
  - Addison, Paul, 1925-1935 (Box 2)
  - Addressograph Co., 1913-1915 (Box 2)
  - Addressograph Co., 1916-1924 (Box 2)
  - Addressograph Sales Agency, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Addresses- Miscellaneous, 1919-1921; 1928-1937 (Box 2)
  - Ade, Charles Hamilton, 1927-1933 (Box 2)
  - Ade, Emmett Milton, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Ade, George, 1917-1937 (Box 2)
  - Ade, Mary, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Ade, Thelma, 1925-1926 (Box 2)
  - Adee, J.N. (Box 2)
  - Adelaide, Sister, 1929-1932 (Box 2)
  - University of Adelaide, 1923-1926 (Box 2)
  - Adelbert College, 1923-1933 (Box 2)
  - Adeline, Cornelius, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Adelphi Academy (College), 1929-1936 (Box 2)
  - Aders, Frieda, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Aders, Jacob, 1914-1928 (Box 2)
  - Aders, O.M., 1922-1936 (Box 2)
  - Aderman, Abe, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adeva, Manuel, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Ernest C., 1932 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Harold C., 1921-1928 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, John T., 1917-1922 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Mildred Virginia, 1922-1930 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Paul W., 1924 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Russel Max, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, Velma, 1919-1923 (Box 2)
  - Adkins, William, 1914-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Arthur E., 1922-1929 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Benjamin, 1031-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Daniel, 1918-1921 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Dave, 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Hymen, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Adler, June, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Adler Planetarium & Astronomical Museum, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Adler, Raymond N., 1932-1934 (Box 2)
  - Administering/Administration/Administrative/Administrator, 1928-1932 (Box 2)
  - Administration Building (William Lowe Bryan Hall) (Box 2)
    - List of communications concerning construction, 1933-1937 (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
      - 1933-1934 (Box 2)
      - 1934-1935, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Application for work on and furnishings, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    - Construction of, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence Concerning Construction- Contractors, Letters, Bidders, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Administration Building- Office Space Requests, Location Recommendations, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Administration Building, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
  - Administration Building- Correspondence re: Inscription, William Lowe Bryan Building, 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - Administration Building, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Admission/Admissions, 1923-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adult Education, 1926-1937 (Box 2)
  - Adult Education Council of Chicago, 1933-1937 (Box 2)
  - Advance Pump & Compressor Co., 1915 (Box 2)
  - Advertisements (Box 2)
    - 1914-1915 (Box 2)
    - 1916-1917 (Box 2)
    - 1918-1920 (Box 2)
  - Advertisement/Advertising, 1922-1937 (Box 2)
  - Advertising Club of Indianapolis, 1922-1925 (Box 2)
  - Advisors, 1934-1936 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee to the Acting President, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Adye, Aner, 1924-1937 (Box 2)
  - Ae-Af, 1923-1937 (Box 2)
  - Ae-Ak, 1914-1937 (Box 2)
  - Aeolian Company, The, 1913-1918 (Box 2)
  - Aeons (Box 2)
    - 1920‑1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926‑1929 (Box 2)
    - 1930‑1932 (Box 2)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 3)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 3)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 3)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 3)
  - Aero Club of America, 1916 (Box 3)
  - Aeronautical Chamber of Commerce of America, Inc., 1931-1933 (Box 3)
  - Aeronautics 1925-1936 (Box 3)
  - Aeronautics (General), 1919 (Box 3)
  - Aeronautics, National Committee for, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Aetna Cabinet Co., 1915-1919 (Box 3)
  - Aetna Casualty and Surety Co., 1926-1937 (Box 3)
  - Aetna Life Ins. Co. (Box 3)
    - 1916-1921 (Box 3)
    - 1929-1936 (Box 3)
  - Aetna Mortgage and Investment Company, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Aetna Trust and Savings, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Afflerbach, Harry, 1933-1937 (Box 3)
  - Africa, 1925-1935 (Box 3)
  - Agate, R.H., 1925 (Box 3)
  - Ageng, Nelle, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
  - Agger, John, 1922-1930 (Box 3)